<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>@shawnr codes</title><link href="http://shawnr.com/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://shawnr.com/feeds/all.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>http://shawnr.com/</id><updated>2017-05-18T10:00:00-07:00</updated><entry><title>Python Education Summit 2017 Notes</title><link href="http://shawnr.com/python-education-summit-2017-notes.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-05-18T10:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2017-05-18T10:00:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Shawn Rider</name></author><id>tag:shawnr.com,2017-05-18:/python-education-summit-2017-notes.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Notes from the Python Ed Summit 2017.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The Python Education Summit is happening on May 18, 2017 in Portland, OR. I am
writing some notes as we go through the day. Apologies to all of the great things
I've missed in these notes (some of the sessions run simultaneously, and I can,
unfortunately, only be in one place at a time).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Keynote: Luciano Ramalho&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Coming with a long history of development and teaching experience, Ramalho
discussed his personal history learning to program as well as some of the
exciting tools and methods of teaching programming in classrooms today. Ramalho
humorously recounted his dismal Study Hall experience when he first moved to
the US, and how the installation of Apple ][ machines in the library liberated
him from the doldrums of sitting quietly in a classroom for an hour.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ramalho asked, appropriately, "Why did only two of us in the whole classroom
take the opportunity to teach ourselves to program?" He discussed with the
audience, which led to lots of ideas about fear of failure or not wanting to be
different from the rest of the group.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think those are all valid points, but I wonder if it was more the result of a
lack of vision: Those kids had no way to understand the valuable benefits they
would get from learning to code. This is something I think many people deal with
today: They don't really know what is involved with writing code, and they have
no idea of how learning to code could be beneficial. It's a reflection of the
poor understanding that people have of coding and software in general.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It seems to me unfair to expect students to be able to realize the benefit of
learning something they have no idea about. It's exceptional when students can
lead themselves to that point, but it's totally understandable why a student
would not be able to get there without help. This is why it's so important to
begin education about coding and software early in our educational careers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Charlotte Chang: Climbing Rocks and Coding Blocks&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Chang dicussed the challenges of learning to code and the ways in which these
challenges can feel intimidating, scary, and dangerous. She made several great
analogies to rock climbing (if you climb, you expect falls; if you code, expect
failures) and generally asserted the idea that learning to code is a risky
endeavor.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Chang's examples and experiences definitely echo with me both personally and
in terms of what I see in my students. There are many examples of students
defeating themselves before they ever really get going due to the fear of
failure, feelings of inadequacy, and generally discouraging experiences of
frustration and exasperation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Jessica Ingrassellino: Teaching a Diverse Classroom&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ingrassellino provided an impromptu talk filling in for a speaker whose Visa was
denied and, therefore, was prevented from attending the conference.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ingrassellino provided a helpful talk discussing ways in which she accommodates
students with diverse needs and abilities in the classroom. She stressed the
need to create a safe space where students could fail without fear, but also
to modulate content to better reach students. She did a good job underlining the
basics of differentiated pedagogy and concerning ourselves with the social
well-being of the classroom.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Lightning Talks&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am not going to provide full summaries of the Lightning Talks (they go too
quickly!), but here are some takeaways:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;PyCon UK has a great Education track!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Logo is still relevant, programming with graphics is fun and good.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Processing with Python is cool.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Helping students learn to ask questions is crucial.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Answers that students discover themselves are much more meaningful and resilient.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Show students what success looks like.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Show students what failure looks like.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Adafruit is a cool company that makes systems on which you can write Python.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><category term="Python"></category><category term="conference"></category><category term="education"></category></entry></feed>